# **Qisheng Pan**

+61 401-937-290 | qisheng.pan@uq.net.au | website

### RESEARCH INTEREST

I studied human genetic variants, investigating the relationship between protein mutations and pathogenic phenotypes. Leveraging computational biophysical measurements and machine learning, my research focuses on providing a guideline of the interpretation of current methods, and the development of new approaches to better characterise the effect of variants.

### **EDUCATION**

**University of Queensland** 

• Doctor of Philosophy (Computational Biology)

University of Melbourne

• Master of Science (Bioinformatic)

**South China Normal University** 

• Bachelor of Science (Biotechnology)

Brisbane, Australia

Jan 2022 - now

Melbourne, Australia 2019-2021

Guangzhou, China

2015-2019

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- 1. **Pan Q**, Portelli S, Nguyen TB et al. Characterization on the oncogenic effect of the missense mutations of p53 via machine learning, Brief Bioinform 2023;25.
- 2. Serghini A, Portelli S, Troadec G et al. Characterizing and predicting ccRCC-causing missense mutations in Von Hippel-Lindau disease, Hum Mol Genet 2023.
- 3. Jessen-Howard D, **Pan Q**, Ascher DB. Identifying the Molecular Drivers of Pathogenic Aldehyde Dehydrogenase Missense Mutations in Cancer and Non-Cancer Diseases, Int J Mol Sci 2023;24.
- 4. Zhou Y, **Pan Q**, Pires DEV et al. DDMut: predicting effects of mutations on protein stability using deep learning, Nucleic Acids Res 2023;51:W122-W128.
- 5. Boer JC, **Pan Q**, Holien JK et al. A bias of Asparagine to Lysine mutations in SARS-CoV-2 outside the receptor binding domain affects protein flexibility, Front Immunol 2022;13:954435.
- 6. **Pan Q**, Nguyen TB, Ascher DB et al. Systematic evaluation of computational tools to predict the effects of mutations on protein stability in the absence of experimental structures, Brief Bioinform 2022;23.
- 7. Han YY, Jin K, **Pan QS** et al. Microglial activation in the dorsal striatum participates in anxiety-like behavior in Cyld knockout mice, Brain Behav Immun 2020;89:326-338.

### **TEACHING EXPERIENCES**

**Instructors**, University of Queensland

Nov 2023

• Advanced Data Visualisation with *ggplot2*: This workshop is the one that I designed, prepared, and delivered, focusing on practical skills on presenting data using *R* and *ggplot2* package.

Teaching Assistant, University of Queensland

Sept 2022

• Computing4lifescience Series (Sept 2022)

### **MENTORSHIP**

**Research Supervisor** (UG: undergraduate, MS: master's)

Georgina Becerra Parra (UG, 2022, UQ), Dana Jessen-Howard (MS, 2023, UQ), Joshua Khoo (MS, 2024, UQ)

# **HONOURS & AWARDS**

Travel Awards of MM2023 conference	Dec 2023
• SCMB Award for Outstanding Contribution to Research (Group Awards)	Nov2023
Student Prize in the CTCMS Seminar	Mar 2023
Comprehensive Student Scholarship	Sept 2016

# RESEARCH EXPERIENCES

Characterising the pathogenic effect of missense mutations via machine learning	2022 - now		
• Leveraged different computational biophysical measurements to annotate missense variants.			
• Developed machine learning models to classify phenotypes of mutations.			
Benchmarking computational biophysical measurements in the absence of experimental	2022 - now		

- Built high-throughput pipeline to generate protein homology models and AlphaFold models.
- Used different metric to assess the predictive performance of various machine learning models.

# **PRESENTATIONS**

structures

1.	Poster presentation in the Lorne Protein Conference 2024 (Australia)	Feb 2024
2.	Oral and poster presentations in the MM2023 conference (Australia)	Dec 2023
3.	Poster presentation in the ABACBS 2023 conference (Australia)	Dec 2023
4.	Research Talk in the 22 <sup>nd</sup> International Conference on Bioinformatics (Australia)	Nov 2023
5.	Lighting talk in the GenGen seminar (UQ)	Apr 2023
6.	6. Oral presentations in the CTCMS seminar (UQ)	
7.	7. Poster presentations in the Lorne Protein Conference 2023 (Australia)	
8.	Poster presentation in the 18 <sup>th</sup> Annual Research Student Symposium (UQ)	Nov 2022
9. Oral presentations in the Joint Biomolecular and Medicinal Chemistry Theme Symposium (UQ)		Apr 2022

# **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Programming: Python, R, Linux Bash, JavaScript

Software: BLAST, MODELLER, PyMol, AutoDock Vina, GALAXY, etc. Machine learning: Random Forest, Neural Network, Feature selection

### **REFEREES**

David B. Ascher	Professor, University of Queensland	d.ascher@uq.edu.au
Thanh-Binh Nguyen	Research Fellow, University of Queensland	thanhbinh.nguyen@uq.edu.au
Stephanie Portelli	Research Fellow, University of Queensland	s.portelli@uq.edu.au
Douglas E.V. Pires	Senior lecturer, University of Melbourne	douglas.pires@unimelb.edu.au
Cheng Long	Professor, South China Normal University	longcheng@m.scnu.edu.cn